<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon those notes which the late Observator [i.e. Henry Parker] hath published upon the seven doctrines and positions which the King by way [of] recapitulation (he saith) layes open so offensive</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3210A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875519</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon those notes which the late Observator [i.e. Henry Parker] hath published upon the seven doctrines and positions which the King by way [of] recapitulation (he saith) layes open so offensive</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to Henry Parker's Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses, followed by "Animadversions animadverted" in answer.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Animadverſions VPON THOSE NOTES Which the late OBSERVATOR hath publiſhed upon the ſeven Doctrines and Poſitions which the KING by way Recapitulation (he ſaith) layes open ſo Offenſive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="animadversions">
            <pb facs="tcp:152172:2"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS VPON thoſe Notes which the late <hi>Obſervator</hi> hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed upon the ſeven <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Poſitions</hi> which the King by way of Recapitulation (hee ſaith) lies open ſo offenſive.</head>
            <div n="1" type="position">
               <head>POSITION I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the Parliament has an abſolute indiſputable power of declaring Law: ſo that all the right of the King and People depends upon their pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>To this the</hi> Obſervator <hi>ſaith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It has beene anſwered, That this power muſt reſt in them, or in the King, or in ſome inferior Court, or els all ſuits will be endleſſe and it cannot reſt more ſafely then in Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION I.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Obſervator</hi> hath contracted his Majeſties words, but hath kept the ſenſe in more generall termes, and ſeemes (though but faintly) to iuſtifie the Poſition, by approving (I know not whoſe anſwer) That this Power can reſt no where more ſafely, then in Parliament. He meanes the Parliament without the King; If he had allowed the King his place in Parliament, I now underſtanding man will eaſily ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribe, That the King in Parliament or the Parliament with him, have an abſolute un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable power, both to make and declare Law; and to end all Suites of what kind ſoever, determinable by humane law within the Kingdome. And here is the moſt ſafe reſting of this Power (and here it hath ever reſted) and not in the King alone (who claimes not that Power, but is willing to governe his ſubjects according to the known Lawes) and much leſſe in a any inferiour Court. But that ſuch an abſolute undiſputable Power of declaring Law, as hath lately beene aſſumed by the Maior part of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſitting Parliament, ſhoud be reſting in them, is neither neceſſary for the ending of ſuites, nor can be, either for King or ſubject. If they may declare that for a Law, a fundamentall Law, which never yet was Enacted, or had any beeing; and deny the plaine undoubted Lawes that have beene Enacted, or fruſtrate them by ſome unheard of interpretation, (as if ſuch interpretation had beene ſome mentall (or rather Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall) reſervation laid up within the Parliament walles, to bee produced upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent occaſions, by their ſucceſſors) they will have ſo full an Arbitrary power, that the right and ſafety of King and people muſt wholly depend upon their Votes. Which power can never be ſafe either for King or People, nor can they produce one preſident that may warrant ſuch preſidents. That the ſecond <hi>Poſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="position">
               <head>POSITION II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat Parliaments are bound to no Preſidents.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <p>
                  <hi>OBSERV.</hi> Statutes are not binding to them, why ſhould then Preſidents? Yet there is no obligation ſtronger then the Honour and Iuſtice of a Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="animadversion">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152172:2"/>
               <head>ANIMAD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERSION II.</head>
               <p>IF Statuts be not binding to them, there is no reaſon that preſidents ſhould be. And he ſaith true, Statutes are not binding to them, that is <hi>de facto,</hi> they are not (for they in ſome things goe directly againſt them) but <hi>de iure,</hi> they are; that is, they ought to be binding to them till they be repealed by the ſame power they were made, that is, by Bill orderly paſſed both Houſes, and ratyfied by his Maieſties Royall aſſent. And unleſſe they can ſhew better reaſon then their bare Aſſertion: Preſidents (as they are the beſt warrant ſo) they are, and ought to be the limits and buonds of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. He might haue ſaid as truly, That Oathes are not binding to them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither Statutes nor Preſidents. But the <hi>Obſervator</hi> tels us (Pag 44.) That the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegance are not endangered by making the Kingdom, and not the King, the proper ſubiect of power. And he yeelds reaſon for it. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he that aſcribes more to the whole Vniverſality, then to the King, yet aſcribes to the King a true Supremacy of Power and Honour above all particulars.</hi> I wonder what he meanes by a true Supremacy of Power and Honour above all perticulars. Surely, he meanes nothing but priority of place, and height of Title; for he is allowed little power over ſome particulars, namely, over the Members of either houſe, and whom elſe they pleaſe to exempt (as they did Serjeant Major <hi>Skippon</hi> for his power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. But this diſtinction helpes them: The Members of either Houſe are ſharers in that Supremacie which is in the Vniverſality and above his; and by the power of that Supremacie they can exempt whom they pleaſe from the power of this, inferiour (pardon the phraſe, abſurdities cannot bee expreſt without a Socleciſme) Supremacie. Uery good: But in good ſober ſadneſſe, doth the <hi>Obſervator</hi> thinke this diſtinction was thought on by the Framers and enjoyners of that Oath, or that the Members of the Houſe, at their entring the Houſe did take their Oath to the King, as to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame over all, with exeption of themſelves, or reſervation of an higher Supremacy to themſelves, when they ſhould be entred? It is hardly credible; Nor doe all (that deſire to tender all due honour to the Parliament) beleeve that they are ſo the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality, or the Kingdome, as the <hi>Obſervator</hi> preſumes. They are truſted by the Vniverſality and Kingdome, and we pray, that they may diſcharge that truſt, not knowing, but that a multitude of men ſubiect (every one of them) to errour, may faile in their Judgement, and being not exempted from the Common condition of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> may poſſibly, not rightly diſcharge the truſt committed to them, as well, as the King, who is blaſted with foule failings, and errours, &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Me thinkes, men that ſo much deteſt Popery, ſhould not borrow the grounds of their reaſoning from them: and I ſhall as ſoone beleeve the Counſell of <hi>Trent,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us that thy are the Univerſall Church, and therefore cannot poſſibly erre, as that the Parliament is the Vniverſall unerring and unpervertibly juſt body of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And ſurely, the Spirit of declaring muſt needs reſide in a ſtrangely large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them, who have power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thus to declare not onely Law, but Oathes too; a greater, then which the Popes flatterers never gave him; and hardly ever any Pope aſſumed ſo great: <hi>Quote conſtringam mutantem Protea nodo?</hi> How ſhall theſe men be bound to doe right, who ſo eaſily unty the knots of theſe ſacred bookes of Law and Oathes? why, yes; There is a bond that will doe it; The obligation of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and honour of a Parliament. But can any man be ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they whom neither Law, Cuſtome, and Preſidents of their Anceſtors, nor Oathes can binde, will bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies held in by the obligation of Juſtice and Honour? Is it not poſſible, that they may (in time) finde a power in themſelves of declaring that obligation voide as well
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152172:3"/>as have done the other? The ſame obligation of Juſtice and Honour, is as ſtrong upon Kings, (and hath ever beene held more powerfull and obſtructiue in them, then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtate mannaged by a community; and yet they dare not truſt his Majeſtie, though ſo obliged. The <hi>Obſervatour</hi> then muſt pardon me, if I deſire, they may rather bee held in, (and hold themſelves ſo to be) by the old obligations of Law. Preſidents, and Oathes, rather then that the Kings liege-people ſhould bee put wholy to conſide to that ſingle oblation of the Juſtice, and Honour of a Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="position">
               <head>POSITION III.</head>
               <p>THat they are Parliaments, and may Iudge of publike neceſsity without the King, and diſpoſe of any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</head>
               <p>They may not deſert the King, but being deſerted by the King, when the Kingdome is in deſtreſſe, they may judge of that diſtreſſe, and relieve it, and are to be accounted by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue of repreſentation as the whole body of the State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION III.</head>
               <p>HIs Majeſty ſets downe this Poſition in more words, but theſe are much to the ſame purpoſe, and upon theſe the inference which his Majeſty makes followes undeniably, That then the life and liberty of the Subject, and all good Lawes made for the ſecurity of them, may be diſpoſed of, and repealed by the Major part of both Houſes, at any time preſent, and by any wayes and meanes procured ſo to bee: And his Majeſty ſhall have no power to protect them. They ſee nothing, that ſee not the miſery, which may follow upon ſuch a vaſt tranſcendency of arbitrary power, if it were inveſted in the Parliament, which (I dare boldly ſay) was never claimed by any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, though in conjunction with (the head of it) the King. Every (the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt) Subject hath ſuch a right and propriety in his goods, that without law, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken from him, though to be imployed for the publike good. And though the ſafety of the people, be the higheſt law and that doe (many times) give a power above other lawes, and againſt them, to the ſupreme magiſtracy in a ſtate, to diſpoſe of private mens eſtates, yet the unchangable rule of Juſtice, muſt have place, even in that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt law, and that requires a compenſation to be made to thoſe, whoſe ſtates or goods are ſo diſpoſed of; and never gives power to uphold the publike good with private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. Nor can it be imagined, that a State upheld, by ſuch helpes, ſhould not be able to make a juſt compenſation to thoſe, by whom it was upheld. But let us heare our <hi>Obſervatour.</hi> They may not (ſaith hee) deſert the King. Gramercy, for that; I am glad to heare they have yet any obligation upon them to tie them to the King. Yet I know not well, what hee meanes by deſerting the King: if he meane it in that ſenſe which he doth the Kings deſerting of them, which (out of queſtion) is his not aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to whatſoever they ſhall thinke fit; Then in reaſon, they ſhould not, by their diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing all his Propoſals, have driven him to diſſent from their, and ſo to have diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them. Well; But being deſerted by the King, when the Kingdome is in diſtreſſe, they may judge of that diſtreſſe, and relieve it. All their power then is upon ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings deſerting them. So that if it appeare, that his Majeſty hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted them (as many good men believe he hath not, in the redreſſe of any reall grieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,) then they have no ſuch power. And however, they claime this power onely when the Kingdome is in diſtreſſe: but how, if the Kingdome be not in diſtreſſe, or (at leaſt) that diſtreſſe be onely or principally cauſed by their claiming of that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152172:3"/>which cannot conſiſt with the Honour and Royall Eſtate of his Majeſty, which all men (by their late Proteſtation) are bound to defend. If it be ſo, that we may eaſily diſcerne how farre they may ſtretch this power, which they claime onely in order to diſtreſſe; and that they may make as much uſe of it, as the Pope doth of his power, in temporalls; <hi>In ordine ad ſpiritualia.</hi> He claimes no more, (though ſome have ſaid, he hath right to more;) and the Parliament will need no more, to do as much as hee takes upon him to do with Chriſtian Princes and States. But they muſt have a right to their power in this caſe of diſtreſſe, whence have they that? why, they have it as the whole body of the State, and that they are, and muſt be ſo accompted, by vertue of repreſentation very good. But let us conſider his words a litle more.</p>
               <p>There is no underſtanding man, but muſt and will acknowledge (unleſſe hee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully derogate from them,) that the Parliament repreſents the body of the State, for thoſe ends, for which they convene, as an Ambaſſadour doth the Prince that ſends him, in the mannage of that buſineſſe for which he is ſent; But this is not an abſolute repreſentation to all intents and purpoſes, beſides, whom doe they repreſent; The body (ſaith hee) of the State. Bee it ſo: but it is onely the body, without the head. And if they were not by repreſentation onely, but really, the whole body of the people (if it were poſſible, they ſhould convene together) they are all but an aſſembly of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, of men to be governed, not to rule, to be commanded, not to command their Head and Soveraigne: and then there can bee no vertue of repreſentation that can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance them to the power, which the <hi>Obſervatour</hi> aſcribes to them, when ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was never in the whole body, which is repreſented. No, never ſuch power in the whole body? I know the <hi>Obſervatours</hi> ſtomack will riſe here. Did not the Peoples conſent, at firſt make Kings and conveigh power into their hands? Truly Sir, not ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but grant it, what then? Marry, he ſaith then it is a principle in nature. <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid efficit tale eſt magis tale;</hi> In Engliſh, If the People make a King, they are more King themſelves, or if they give power, they have more power: and may reſume and exerciſe that power when they pleaſe. Excellent learning, and well applyed, I believe he learned this piece from <hi>Suarez</hi> the Ieſuite. But the <hi>Obſervatour,</hi> may know; that that rule admits many limitations: and ſurely, it holds onely <hi>In cauſis totalibus,</hi> which the People are not in the conſtitution of Kings. But ſuppoſe their conſent, did at firſt give power to Kings; when their conſent is given for them and their Succeſſours to a King and his Heires, can the ſucceeding People cut off the entaile, and retract the conſent their Anceſtors have given? By what right? with what juſtice? I know not, but the People may contract for them and their Succeſſours in the conveighance of Soveraigne power (if ever they had it in their hands to give) as any man may in the conveighance of his lands or goods: and that ſuch conveighance may be as binding to Succeſſours in the one as in the other: and then I am ſure they cannot have power at all times, and in all ſucceeding ages to reſume what they have ſo given. Our Kings right (ſo farre as it is derived from the People) is of this kind. And if hee had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grounds for his claime of Soveraignty, (as it is moſt certaine, that he hath) ſuch a conſent once granted, were ſufficient to binde the People that it cannot ever be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them by a major part of them (comming in with their <hi>Nolumus hunc reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare ſuper nos</hi>) to deprive him of that right. But ſurely, they would never make ſo abſolute a grant of their power to Princes as to deveſt themſelves of it. Good Sir, ſhew me that proviſo in their grant. But it ſeemes to you unnaturall they ſhould: I doe not wonder it ſhould ſeeme ſo to you, who make it agreeable to the <hi>Cleareſt beames of humane reaſon, and the strongeſt inclinations of nature,</hi> (and by conſequence, as you would perſwade the world, juſtifiable;) <hi>For every private man to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152172:4"/>by force if aſſaulted though by the force of Magiſtrate, or his owne Father, and though hee bee not without all confidence by flight &amp;c.</hi> I wiſh whileſt you have ſuch recourſe to nature, you would not forget Chriſtianity, which teaches ſubjection and obedience, and gives no liberty; (either to privat men, or the maior part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty) of reſiſtance, but ſaith, they that reſiſt <hi>ſhall receive to themſelves damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And if the <hi>Obſervator</hi> be a Gentleman, he ſhould tender how he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to nature in point of right, leaſt he give occaſion to ſome <hi>Wat Tyler's</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, to preach againe upon that text.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Adam</hi> dolue and <hi>Eve</hi> ſpan,</l>
                  <l>Who was then a Gentleman.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>He may find a goodly Sermon upon the text, ſet downe by <hi>Iohn Stow</hi> in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and ſuch Doctrine delivered upon it, the uſe, of which would ſhake his title to his inheritance, and the name of Gentleman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="position">
               <head>POSITION IV.</head>
               <p>That no Member of the Parliament ought to be troubled for Treaſon, &amp;c. without leave.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</head>
               <p>This is intended of ſuſpitions onely; and when leave may ſeaſonably bee had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And when competent accuſers appeare not in the impeachment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANMADVERSION IV.</head>
               <p>HIs Majeſty hath ſaid ſo much of this and ſo little of it hath beene anſwered, (or indeed is anſwerable,) that I ſhall not need to ſay muach. Onely I obſerve the modeſty of this <hi>Obſervatour;</hi> that he doth not abſolutely ſay, they are not to be troubl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thoſe crimes; but not upon ſuſpition onely, &amp;c. I know not what he may call ſuſpitions, but I beleeve, the beſt evidences, may eaſily be held for bare ſuſpitions, if they may not have liberty to ſpeake out; and that they cannot have, unleſſe the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer be firſt in ſafe cuſtody, and brought to triall where they may legally be produced, And, I beleeve, few wiſe men will thinke it reaſonable, that the grounds of ſuſpition of Treaſon, ſhould enceſſarily be opened before triall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="position">
               <head>POSITION V.</head>
               <p>THat the Soveraigne Power reſides in both Houſes of Parliament: The King having no negative Voyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</head>
               <p>This power is not claimed as ordinary, nor to any purpoſe; but to ſave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from ruine, and in caſe, where the Kingdome is ſo ſeduced, as that he prefers dangerous men, and perſecutes his loyall Subjects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION V.</head>
               <p>HIs Majeſty infers upon this Poſition. <hi>That himſelfe muſt be Subject to their Commands.</hi> This ſounds, but harſhly in the eares of loyall Subjects; That any poſture wherein they can be put, can raiſe Subjects to a capacity of Soveraignty, and reduce, their Soveraigne to become their Subject. But he comforts us here, and tels us, this power is not claimed as ordinary nor to any purpoſe, &amp;c. This is but poore comfort, it is not but it may be in good time, if they pleaſe. He doth not ſay, they ſhall not hereafter, or cannot claime it as ordinary, and to other purpoſes then that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152172:4"/>names. So that there may be other cauſes, that may make them claime this power, as well as this. But indeed, they need no more, if it be in their power to declare that to be the caſe of the King and Kingdome when they pleaſe. But they will never doe it, but where there is a juſt cauſe for it; and the truth leades them to it. Truely, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve honourably of the Iuſtine and Wiſedome of Parliaments; but I do beleeve, that they are not either infallible, or that they cannot poſſibly doe amiſſe. And the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatour</hi> muſt bring better arguments; (and I feare, he cannot bring ſo good to make me beleeve otherwiſe,) then ever yet were brought for the infallibility of a generall Councell. But I have ſaid enough for the preſent of the reſidence of Soveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Parliament, and the ground of their claime to it, <hi>by the vertue of repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in my third <hi>Animadverſion.</hi> J ſhall here onely give the Reader a briefe gloſſe upon the language here uſed by the <hi>Obſervatour.</hi> To ſave the Kingdome from ruine, (that is, from Monrachy or being goverued by the King. The King is ſeduced,) that is, he is perſwaded (by his owne underſtanding, and other evill Counſellours,) not to part with Soveraignty, nor to become a Subject to his Subjects. He prefers danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, (that is, ſuch as would have him ſtill to be their King proſecutes his loyall Subjects,) that is, ſuch as would rule him, and the people at their pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="position">
               <head>POSITION VI.</head>
               <p>THat the levying of forces againſt the perſonall commands of the King, (though accompanied with his preſence) is not levying of warre againſt the King: but warre againſt his authority, not Perſon, is warre againſt the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATOVR.</head>
               <p>If this were not ſo, The Parliament ſeeing a ſeduced King, ruinating himſelfe, and the Kingdome, could not ſave both, but ſtand and looke on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION VI.</head>
               <p>I Thought this Poſition ſo ſtrangly Paradoxall, and ſo apparently contrary to reaſon and common ſenſe, that no man would have appeared in defence of it. Yet this <hi>Obſervator</hi> never bluſhes, nor blinkes at it, but affirmes it ſtoutly. But for all that I ſhall beleeve very ſlowly, That the Kings perſon can at any time bee without his Authority: Or that they may deſtroy the Kings Perſon, to preſerve the King. My Faith is not ſtrong enough to beleeve theſe ſublime points, and myſteries of State: I ſhall ſubſcribe thus farre, That warre againſt the Kings Authority, (though in the abſence of his Perſon) is warre againſt the King: But that the King and his perſon ſhould be in two places, will never (I feare) downe with me. But however Ile ſee his reaſon: What's that? <hi>Why elſe the Parliament ſeeing a ſeduced King running him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Kingdome could not ſave both, but muſt ſtand and looke on.</hi> Surely this reaſon is full of waight, and ready to burſt, it is big with probability. I ſupoſe the <hi>Reader</hi> underſtands his language heere, by my former gloſſe; But if wee ſhould take the words as they ſound the reaſon would ſeeme as ſtrange, as that which is brought to confirme. The King running himſelfe and his Kingdome, a mad King, or an Ideot (hee meanes) and then 'twas fit the Parliament appointed him a gardian. <hi>Ruining himſelfe and his Kingdome.</hi> Is it poſſible; That the King ſhould ruine himſelfe and his Kingdome. What? The King alone? Is he alone able to doe it without the people? It is hardly credible? If he have the people on his ſide, and a pevailing Major party, I thinke the <hi>Obſervator</hi> (ſtanding to his owne Principles) will not deny that hee hath Soveraigne power with him, and that it is unnaturall to thinke the Community ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152172:5"/>deſtroy it ſelfe. But the Community (hee will ſay) is to be looked at in Parliament. Well, But good Sir, may not the people withdraw the power of reprentation, which they granted to the Parliament; was their grant ſo abſolute, and ſo irrevocable, that they diſpoſſeſt themſelves wholy of taking or exerciſing that power, their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per perſons? Remember your principles about the conveying of Soveraigne power into the hands of Kings; and if you can ſhew no better Cards for their power of repreſentation, then the Peoples revocable conſent, (and I would faine know why it ſhould be more revocable from Kings then men) you will finde their tenure in it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tickle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="position">
               <head>POSITION VII.</head>
               <p>THat according to ſome Parliamente they may depoſe Kings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observation">
               <head>OBSRVATOR.</head>
               <p>Tis denied that any King was depoſed by a free Parliament, fairely elected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION VII.</head>
               <p>I Like this note better then all the reſt, and am wholy of his minde: That never any free Parliament, fairely elected, depoſed any King: and I hope (whatſoever his principles ſeemes to inſinuate) they doe not beleeve they have power to doe it, and pray that they may never attempt, (at leaſt, not to be able to depoſe the King, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Monarchy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="protestation">
               <head>The Authors Proteſtation.</head>
               <p>HAving finiſhed theſe ſudden <hi>Animadverſions:</hi> I doe proteſt in the preſence of Almighty God, with my life, power, and eſtate to maintaine and defend ſo farre as lawfvlly I may, the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion. His Maieſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Honour and Royall Eſtate, The juſt Liberties of the Subject, and the power and priviledges of Parliament (ſo farre as I ſhall bee able to know or underſtand them) and to doe all other things contained in the late <hi>Proteſtation.</hi> And this I doe ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from my heart, beleeve my ſelfe to be under the guilt of Perjury if I faile in any one thing here proteſted. And therefore ſhall never hold my ſelfe abſolved by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving one, if I violate it in any other part. I ſhall ever defend his Majeſties Perſon, Honour, and Royall Eſtate, as my ſole Soveraigne, and the Parliament (next under him) in the higheſt capacity of Subjects as the Supreame Judicatory, the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell and Body Repreſentative of this Kingdome. And I pray, that all thoſe that doe cot joyne with me, may either ſpeedily be converted or confounded.</p>
               <closer>Faxit Deus.</closer>
               <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb facs="tcp:152172:5"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS ANIMADVERTED.</head>
            <head type="sub">Or a Reply to the late <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon thoſe Notes which a late Obſervator publiſhed upon the ſeven Doctrines and Poſitions which the King by way of Recapitulation layes open ſo offenſive.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Animadverſor hath attackt the Obſervator, juſt like a weak and degenerous enemy, that durſt not encounter his adverſary in open field, but lodgeth himſelf in ſome obſcure and ignoble paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, to attempt at leaſt upon his Arriere-guard, not being able to pierce into his main body. The ingenious peruſer of both, I doubt not, may diſcern that the Obſervator in the concluſion of his Treatiſe onely recapitulated ſeven Refults out of His Majeſties papers, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to his Antecedent diſquiſition, and the Parliaments proceedings, that ſo one might compend ouſly view the ſubject of his diſcourſe, and as it were by an Index find out the conſutation of His Majeſties poſitions, by the fore-going Arguments of the book, which the Animadverſor very cautelouſly is pleaſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to take notice of in the whole Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt poſition, the Animadverſor grants the Obſervators Arguments for the declarative power of Parliament in reſpect of the ſafe reſidence of that power in the boſome of the Jutelary Aſſembly; But with this reſtriction, <q>That he ſhould have allowed he King his place in Parliament, and not have named a Parliament without him.</q> But how could the Obſervator without affronting impudence ſpeak otherwiſe? ſeeing His Majeſtie in preſent is pleaſed actually to have his reſidence out of Parliament, and will not allow himſelf a place in it; but inſtead of concurrence with it, ſeeks the remoteſt diſtances from it. The better therefore to ſee how the King and Parliament are in parts we will firſt negatively and then poſitively open the preſent Controverſie betwixt them, which is the cauſe of their disjunction. Which in the firſt place is not this which moſt men conceive. That when His Majeſtie ſhall agree, and the Parliament likewiſe agree, for eſtabliſhing ſome new Law or interpreting ſome old, which may be for the particular commoditie of ſome conditions of men onely, in the common-wealth; Whether then the King ought to declare this or that to be Law excluſively of the Parliament, or the Parliament do the ſame excluſively of the King: But po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively it is this, When there is viſibly a danger readie to confound the whole common-wealth, and conſequently all particular commodities and perſons, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the State if then convened, may not lawfully of it ſelf provide for its preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, eſpecially if the King either ſee not the danger, or ſeeing it will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for it in ſuch manner as may give beſt ſecuritie to Himſelf and Common-wealth: When therefore ſuch a Queſtion ſhall juſtly ariſe betwixt King and Common-wealth (which collectively is that we call a Parliament) it being of publike intereſt of State, and ſo <hi>De jure publico,</hi> it cannot fall under the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any inferiour judicature (with which thoſe ſo known voted Laws, the Animadverſor ſpeaks of, are to be found). For that is furniſht onely with rules of particular (not univerſall) juſtice, for the deciſion of particular differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this or that man, for this or that thing. Which rules being too narrow for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152172:6"/>ſo capacious a ſubject, we muſt recurre to thoſe that the originall Laws of Nature and Policy hold out to us, which muſt needs be ſuperior to the other. The chiefeſt rule of that is, <hi>Ne quovismodo periclitetur respublica,</hi> That by all means publike ſafety be ſecured: And every State muſt principally endeavour to hold faſt and ſure our publike ſociable Incorporations one with another, from publike diſtreſſes, calamities, and deſtructions, which may ariſe from our ſelves or other forraign Kingdoms; And whileſt that is done according as Natures Laws and Policy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in Univerſall juſtice, then may well in the mean time proceed to make or reviſe Laws of Particular juſtice, which is of particular things, whereby we may commutatively encreaſe our fortunes and eſtates one by another, or by forraign commerce. But if thoſe that ſit at the head of the Commonwealth ſhall let looſe the holm of it, and ſo let it float at all hazards, or elſe unadviſedly ſteere it direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards rocks and ſhelves, It ſelf is bound by thoſe original Laws (which ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be ſome means) to ſave it ſelf from a wrack: And how the King is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded or wrong'd by having himſelf and his Kingdom preſerved from imminent danger, and how it is poſſible a King may ruine his Kingdom, follow in its juſt place. In the mean time from theſe premiſſes we prove that the Parliaments me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod is moſt excellent; For in the firſt place it endeavours to ſecure the being of the Common-wealth now floating at hazard; And afterwards to apply its ſelf to quicken particular Laws for our well-being. <hi>Now therefore the fundamentall Law which the Animadverſor ſo hotly cals for, and the Parliaments ſquares by is not ſuch a one as (ſome ſay) was never known before it was broken; Nor (as he ſaies) lies mentally or parliamentally in the walls of the Parliament Houſe to be produced upon any emergent occaſion:</hi> But is ſuch a one as is coucht radically in Nature it ſelf, (and ſo becomes the very pin of law and ſociety) and is written and enacted irrepealably in her <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which we are not beholden to any ſublunary power for, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to us as we are living and ſociable creatures. And no known act of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Juſtice or right to this or that petty thing, can claſh with this, but muſt in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vail to it, as to its ſuperintendent. For what can thoſe particular Acts of Law, which are to encreaſe our private and domeſtick profit advantage us? when it's doubtfull in ſo great dangers whether we may enjoy our lives at all, or no. It is therefore notoriouſly calumnious and inconſequent which the Animadverſor from hence affirms, <hi>That the Parliament affects an arbitrary power,</hi> or the particular rights in ordinary courſe of Juſtice, as alſo the ſafety of King and people muſt at all times totally depend on their Votes excluſively of the King: Which in the following Poſition comes to be more fully diſproved: Which power we confeſſe with him can never be ſafe either for King or people, nor is Preſidentable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Poſiti.</hi> Parliaments are not bound to preſidents (ſaith the Obſervator) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not to Statutes; <hi>viz.</hi> Abſolutely; For the cauſe both of the one and the other is not permanent: And it's true therefore which the Animadverſor ſaith, <hi>that they are durable, till they be repealed,</hi> which had been to good purpoſe had he ever denied it. For he rightly attributes no more power to Statutes then to other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Laws (which (as is proved in the firſt Poſition, and further ſhall be in this) cannot in his caſe ſtand in equity, nor act beyond their power, and that contrary to the Legiſlative intent, <hi>viz.</hi> to be a violation of ſome more ſoveraign good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceable, or ſome extreme and generall evil avoidable; which evill otherwiſe might ſwallow not onely Statutes but all other ſanctions what ever. And thus in reſpect of the effect, they may be ſaid in ſome ſort to Repeal themſelves: For real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152172:6"/>in ſuch a caſe they become mortified, and can do no more for us. For the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments caſe and controverſie (which the Animadverſor ſtill forgets to be of preſerving the whole Kingdom, and ſo, <hi>De jure publico</hi>) is of ſo tranſcendent a nature, "That <hi>de facto</hi> it may not, and <hi>de jure</hi> it ought not to be reſtrained by pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mortified Statutes or Laws, in acting ſo much good for us. <hi>But how ſhould Preſidents</hi> (as the Animadverſor ſaith) <hi>be best warrants? or how ſhould they be in the like degree limiting or binding that Oaths are?</hi> I beſeech ye conſider the conſequence, Such or ſuch a Parliament did not, or durſt not do this or that; therefore may no Parliament do it? Some Parliaments (not comparable to the Worthies of this) have omitted ſome good out of ſupineneſſe, ſome out of difficulty, to avoid a greater evil, which might be valuable with the good deſired; ſome perhaps hath done ill, which the integritie and worth of this abhors to think of; ſo that neither King nor Parliament have reaſon to plead ſo ſtrongly for coherence to Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. But both have better rules if they will not decline them, which are, To di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all by the intereſt of State, (which is never accuſable of Injuſtice) And by Equitie, which we may call a generall Law: And, though it be variable according to the ſubject matter and circumſtances, yet it is that onely, which will not let <hi>ſummum jus,</hi> be <hi>ſumma injuria,</hi> which is the ſupremeſt right that can be done us. And it remains to be wiſht that the Animadverſor would have ſhown us in this main buſineſſe, wherein the Parliament hath gone croſſe, either to publike intereſt of State, or Equity. <hi>To ſay</hi> (as the Animadverſor doth) <hi>that this ſingle and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſe excludes the King from Supremacy (even above particulars) and diveſts him to the naked priority onely of Place and Title,</hi> is that which blaſts it ſelf, unleſſe the Animadverſor be able to prove the Kings exerciſe of his former power totally intercepted, and the more now then in other Parliaments of the like circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or that he is ruin'd by having his Kingdom preſerved. <hi>But Serjeant Major Skippon (who is a particular) was not permitted, to obey the Kings ſummons of him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King</hi> (ſaith the Animadverſor) <hi>is denied a power even above particulars.</hi> But we anſwer that his caſe reports to that of the Parliaments, and muſt ſtand or fall with the equity of that. In the mean time he is ſo imployed, that he could not have been in any more redounding to His Majeſties ſolid happineſſe, which (rightly underſtood) would have produced rather an excuſe then an accuſation. <hi>For the Parliaments diſcharging of their truſt</hi> (which the Animadverſor fears ſo much) It is ſo notorious to all uncorrupted and unbiaſt judgements, that we have reaſon to pray, that thoſe who ſo adviſedly elected them, in a time of leſſe danger to the Kingdom, then this preſent is, be not more diſloyall to them, then they are to their chuſers. What they have actually effected with the Kings concurrence, the Animadverſor I hope, will not except againſt; and what they deſire further to effect (wherein they ſo humbly and patiently have attended his Majeſties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence) is onely for the happier continuation of that other to us, and is to be reputed good or ill, in order to that. Where then is the evill for which the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be ſo ſcourged by all ſort of hands? why did we engage them ſo ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to wipe off that Ruſt, which began to eat ſo deep into the letter of our laws, and all our poſſeſſions? and to make new purchaſes for us of all our eſtates? if now being aſſembled they cannot diſcern what and where thoſe laws are to be found, by the luſter and power of which they ſhould act all this for us. We have bleſſings plentifully in ſtore for his Majeſtie, but deſire he would not reduce the ultimate reſolution and reſerch of Law (our bleſſing) to be in his own boſome, more then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152172:7"/>in that of the Parliaments, leſt when God in his anger ſhall deprive us of ſo great a bleſſing as is his life and government, that die with him. I ſhall not multiply on the Animadverſors Arguments; <hi>Of the poſſibility of the Parliaments erring, and not rightly diſcharging their truſts:</hi> all which might be more powerfully urged on one man confiding in his own ſingularity. He might have known them to have been unanſwerably refuted, and kild before their birth. But ſince he will have the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament "ſo great practicians of Popiſh policy, in reſpect of ſome infallibilitie, which he ſaies, and they never arrogated; ſave onely a probability of leſſe erring in that queſtion betwixt his Majeſtie and themſelves; let me, I ſay, nakedly recite what the learned and yet unanſwered Divine in this matter (which the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſor ſo triumphs in) hath urged againſt the Papiſts, whom it moſt concerns, ſo to leave the Reader to aſſume what ſhall ſeem moſt deducible to himſelf; His words are theſe. <note place="margin"> Chilling. c. <hi>2</hi> p. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> * He that would uſurp an abſolute tyranny and lordſhip over any people, need not put himſelf to the trouble and difficulty of abrogating his Laws, made to maintain the common liberty; for he may fruſtrate their intent and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe his deſign as well, if he can get the power and authority to interpret them as he pleaſes, and have his interpretations ſtand for laws. I ſhall not need to reca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate the condition of our Laws before the Parliament, nor yet what interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations they received; Which interpretations were held ſo Authentique, that they made the Law but a noſe of wax, to wring ſome times this way, for Ship-money, and for the lawfulneſſe of it, as to make the King likewiſe the ſole Judge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſer of all publike dangers, ſometimes another way for legall monopolies, &amp;c. Let the world then judge who arrogate moſt infallibility, or have more made uſe of Papiſts or Popiſh policy.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Obſervator ſaith that the Parliament deſerted by the King in the whole Kingdoms diſtreſſe may relieve it and the King. Here is aſſerted the publique In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of State, which can fall under no notion of any inferiour Court to examine. But the Animadverſor draws this conſequence from thence; <hi>That then every mans eſtate may be wreſted from his propriety and poſſeſſion: Quàm urceus exit.</hi> Here he doth moſt palpably diſcover the looſeneſſe of his Logick and cauſe, and how little he holds to his premiſſes, and ſtate of the Controverſie betwixt King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I ſo oft noted before; and ſhewed the caſe to be <hi>De jure publico,</hi> and ſo politicall.</p>
            <p>Commutative therefore and Diſtributive Juſtice being of inferior matters, have their inferior Courts, and the apparant letter of the Law to decide, and power to actuate what is rightly decided. But this controverſie being <hi>De jure publico,</hi> of a publike right, it fals under the notion of another ſort of Juſtice, whereas particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proprieties and poſſeſſions, fall under thoſe two inferior ſorts of Juſtice, as hath been proved in the concluſion of the firſt Poſition, which together with this ſhew the ſandineſſe and incoherence of the Animadverſors conſequence. Here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will onely note, that even in a common diſtreſſe (which is leſſe then a publique) without a Vote of Parliament, or expecting any other diſpenſation of Right, a particular propriety may be deſtroyed by a Community to preſerve it ſelf: As when the Sea breaks in upon a County, a bank may be made of and on this or that mans ground whether he pleaſe or no; And when our Neighbour <hi>Vcalcyons</hi> houſe blazes, frequently wee ſee ſome houſes pluckt down (where the fire actually broke not out) leſt it ſhould conſume the whole ſtreet. And equitie (before Poeſie) that in reſpect of the propinquitie of the danger, we are ſuppoſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152172:7"/>to be even in the danger it ſelfe; and that the houſe ſo pluckt downe, is not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſo much to be dilapidated as burnt.</p>
            <q>Tuns tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>But I wonder by what Act or Declaration the Parliament hath denyed a compenſation to the ſufferer in that kinde, as the Queſtion now ſtands?</hi> If all men did not know that the Parliament hath ſo provided for the indemnity of thoſe at <hi>Hull,</hi> perhaps the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſor might have gained the credit of ſome modeſtie in averring, <hi>That the Parliament upholds publike good with private miſery.</hi> With the like grace alſo, and with ſufficient confidence doth he tell us; <hi>That if there be a great diſtreſſe in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it is cauſed by the Parliaments claiming that power which cannot conſiſt with the Royall eſtate of his Majeſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis prodigious to all honeſt underſtandings, That the neare engagements of warre with the <hi>Scotts</hi> twice meerly upon miſunderſtandings; That the deſigne of ſtrangling the Parliament as ſoone as it was borne (for proofe of which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament preſumes to have had too much ſufficiency) That having the bloudieſt and true Papiſticall warre in <hi>Ireland</hi> rayſed againſt our Nation, and that againſt the Parliament eſpecially (in the walls of whoſe houſe they have already endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered the a breach, <hi>Jam perlucente ruinâ.</hi>) That even now among our ſelves we ſee ſome, who with more alacrity are ready to employ themſelves againſt that ſacred Aſſembly, than againſt thoſe unchriſtian Rebells, and yet that all this ſhould be too little to evince the Realitie (as the Animadverſor ſaith) of a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Kingdome; and who is yet more tranſcendent, That all this ſhould be cauſed by the Parliament, which aymes at nothing but the extirpation of the Parliament root and branch, and of which ſome part of it (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Scotch</hi> troubles) had being long before the Parliament had any; and then I pray, how could it be the cauſe of it? How the King is head and we the body, and how the King cannot be inſulted over by having his Kingdome and Selfe preſerved from ruine, is proved at large by the Obſerver, beyond the capacitie of any his animadverſions. Whether the people may revoke all they actually have tranſacted to their King, is a Queſtion very impertinently inſerted by the Animadverſor, in reſpect of any thing that the Obſervator hath in the Parliaments caſe; which is ſuch, That when the King ſhall have endeavoured his utmoſt, he will finde, that he ſhall not be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Kingdome in extremitie of diſtreſſe, without the aſſiſtance of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe. However this the Obſervator denies, that the people could make ſuch a conveyance of power to their Kings, as might prove deſtructive of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: So that much of the Animadvertors Divinitie might have been husbanded for an aptor occaſion. Neverthelſſe, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> in the 13. of the <hi>Romans,</hi> tells us not what power is the higheſt, but that that power which is the higheſt ought to be obeyed. Againe, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks firſt of a few particular diſperſt men, and thoſe againe in a primitive condition; who had no means to provide for their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Moreover, its very obſervable that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> in the 3. verſe ſpeaks of a Ruler, as our Law ſpeaks of our King, <hi>viz.</hi> That he is not a terror to good, but to evill workes: The Law likewiſe ſaith, The King can doe no injuſtice. The interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the one muſt ſquare with the other, and that muſt be according to the diſtinction of Fact and Right. For according to Fact, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Ruler may be a torror to good, and a cheriſhing to evill workes; but by Right he ought not to be ſo. Our Law ſayth, Our King rather ought not in Right, than that <hi>de Facto</hi> he cannot doe injuſtice; For we know there have been both unjuſt Kings, and ill
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152172:8"/>Rulers. But leaſt there ſhould be ſuch, Scripture it ſelfe, as well as our Parliament, doth endeavour to binde them from exerciſing ill. As <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. ver. 18, 19, 20. The King ſhall have a booke to learne to keepe the Law, and to doe according to it, leaſt his heart be lifted up above his brethren. And <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46.18. The Prince may not take of the peoples inheritance by oppreſſion, and thruſt them out of it, but ſhalbe content with his own poſſeſſion, leaſt other men be ſcattered from their poſſeſſions. Wherein then hath the Parliament denyed the King that due which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> allowes his Ruler? Who he ſaith (as is very obſervable through the whole Chapter) that he may be a Miniſter to us onely for good: And to keepe the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament even with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> What elſe doth it hazard it ſelfe for, but for refuſing to favour the King in an uncircumſcribed power of doing ill? Which facultie he vindicates to himſelfe irreſtrainably, And that by vertue of ſome Right and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of Law and Religion, even to doe all manner of ill, if ſo be he ſhall ever be pleaſed ſo to doe. Moreover, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath not, nor could any where repeale the lawes of nature, ſo that if the Parliament in its caſe hath neither declin'd them, nor our own Originall Contracts, nor the preſent intereſt of State, nor S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> Then I hope, it hath kept it ſelfe conſonantly to Law and Religion.</p>
            <p>Out of all this (with what followes in the ſixth Poſition) wee may eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer "to the Animadverſors Objection of Reſiſtance. For out of thoſe premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it appeares, That in the King there are two things onely; Firſt, His Perſon; Secondly, His office, authoritie, or as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, his Power. For his perſon, we hold it alwayes inviolable: For his power or office, becauſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects us onely for good, us very reaſonable that we apply our ſelves in obedience to that, for our owne ſakes as well as for his. But the Court Paraſites they are not content with this diſtribution, but adde to the perſon and power or office of a Prince, that which they call, The will or pleaſure of a Prince; or rather they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the power or office of a Prince to his Will: And ſo by that ſubtill conjunction they proving them all one <hi>(Quia omnis poteſtas eſt voluntatis)</hi> then they aske us the Queſtion, Whether we are not equally bound to obey the one in all latitudes as well as the other? As if we had contracted for the evill as well as the good, and that, as it ſhould ſeem beſt to the Prince we contracted with. But to that we clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier anſwer, That becauſe the will lies under an indifferency of commanding the ill, as well as the good, we may lawfully embrace that part and power onely of his will which is to good, (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) which indeed is the very eſſence of his power, and makes him a King: and we may reject the other, which makes him a bloudy Tyrant: Yet not ſo as to violate his perſon in any caſe, (no more than <hi>David</hi> would King <hi>Saul</hi>) but preſervatively to thruſt as farre from us as we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, all other bloud-ſuckers, who are forward to execute on us his ruining com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; becauſe in ſuch a caſe he contracts his own ruine as well as ours, and is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be in a diſtemper, and in ſtead of a wholeſome potion to call for poyſon, which I thinke, no good or honeſt Phyſitian would obey, but rather reſiſt thoſe that would obey him. Wherefore in theſe conſiderations, it is not here as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverſor ſaith of the Parliament; <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare ſuper nos;</hi> but, <hi>Nolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hos deſtruere nos.</hi> But of this in the ſixth Poſition. And for this hath been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, I know I quote our owne Gracious Prince, who hath been pleaſed thus to indoctrinate us in his ſeverall Proteſtations, of venturing his own life to preſerve us in the fruition of our due liberties of Subjects; which we are ſure we cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy from him, if by that Proteſtation he intended to force upon us a duty and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152172:8"/>of embracing all thoſe tormentors whom he ſhould ſend to us at any time, on any occaſion (lawfull or not lawfull) to ſpoyle us either of our lives or ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; If ſo be ſo much evill ſhould poſſibly hereafter enter into his Majeſties ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred thoughts and will. Of which therefore ſeeing there is never a knowne Law of the Land, and that it hath no analogie with the true Proteſtant Religion, and our own juſt liberties of Subjects, we will preſume that his Majeſtie abhorres the thought of chaining us to ſuch a ſlavery for his own part, both in Fact &amp; Right; though alas he cannot promiſe us that all his Succeſſors ſhall do the like. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Animadverſor doth plainly abuſe his Majeſtie in this Argument, &amp; doth deſperately corrupt his preſent cauſe. Thus we ſee what evils we may thruſt from us, and how we are bound to preſerve the Kings power or office, together with his perſon, as much as our own. But the Animadverſor, together with his Tribe, preach another kinde of doctrine, from whence they know how to raiſe better uſes for their ends, than the King can doe any; And that is, That inſtead of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the worſt of thoſe evills which a Kings bare pleaſure may be that we ſhould ſuffer by the hands of other perſons, that we ſhould I ſay, ſimply betake our ſelves to flight, leaving all that we have in this world, but our lives, to the Kings diſpoſall, and to be transferred to thoſe whom he ſhall thinke better wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of them than our ſelves. But in the Parliaments caſe it hath been obſerved, that as it is impoſſible (in a manner) for a whole Kingdome to flie, ſo ſurely can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not that be required of it: This eaſe is not as <hi>Davids</hi> (a particular mans) was, who being in the right yet in danger, fled indeed, but it was from one place to ſtand better on his guard in another.</p>
            <p n="4">4 No Member of Parliament ought to be troubled for Treaſon upon ſuſpition onely; eſpecially, I ſay, in ſuch a caſe, whereof not onely the whole Houſe, but the whole Kingdome knowes it ſelfe to be a like culpable. And that the accuſed were in ſafe cuſtody, is not to be doubted of by the Animadverſor, if the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a whole Kingdome can give ſecuritie which is ſufficient enough for five men, for ought the Amimadverſor hath to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Becauſe the Parliament to ſave a whole Kingdome once from ruine, hath uſed ſome power which is communicable to a whole Kingdom in ſuch an extraordinary caſe; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may (ſaith the Animadverſor) uſurpe it in ordinary caſes; becauſe it may declare the danger what it will at pleaſure, and it is not infallible.</hi> As this conſequence of the Animadverſor is the ſame with that of the third Poſition, ſo may the anſwer of that be applyed to this, to which I ſhall refer the Reader. This onely will I adde, That there is no need to create an Infallibilitie in the Parliament to diſcerne mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact within every mans cognizance; but to afford it onely a probabilitie of leſſe erring or being leſſe deceived rather than a particular Individuall; And that it's common intereſt joyned with its indirectneſſe and integritie (of which the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary exact chooſing of the Members at the beginning, it is an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary proofe) may be a forcible Improbabilitie of its ever uſurping ſuch a power in ordinary caſes, which as it cannot be ſerviceable any way to us (becauſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſes have their moſt convenient courſes certainly regulated) ſo can it not be but extreamly dangerous to themſelves alone, and no wayes advantageous; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ſuch caſes we participate all of us of the like conveniences. This Poſition the Animadverſor is pleaſed to conclude with a Ridle; <hi>That the ruine which the Parliament intends to ſave the Kingdome from, is to ſave it from Monarchy.</hi> — <hi>Riſum teneatis amici?</hi> Are we ſo overgrowne with that government, which our Lawes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152172:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>are lockt and cabenetted in, in ſuch manner, that the wounding of the one is the bleeding of the other? Or is it true w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Biſhops have ſo long pulpited at Court, that the raiſing of their power muſt be the Ecclipſe of the other? although we know, and all the world with us, That Monarchy was of a more extended lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and abſoluteneſſe before Chriſtianity was profeſt by any Monarch, than ever it was ſince: Or more coherently to the Animadverſors owne words; Can there be no abuſes or Cobwebs in Church or Common-wealth, but they muſt needs be ſpun out of the bowells of Monarchy? ſo that the reforming and ſweeping away of the one, muſt needs be the ſweeping away of the other? For our own parts, we will not make them ſo much Sonne and Father, although the Animadverſor be pleaſed to doe his Majeſtie this good ſervice. What then, the too too true ruine of the Kingdome is conceived to be, is ſet downe in the third Poſition; And what Connexion there is in making Monarchy the ſame with that, let the refined'ſt and the rudeſt Logick collect.</p>
            <p n="6">6.7. <hi>Whether levying of Forces againſt the perſonall Commands of the King, though accompanied with his preſence, be to war againſt the King,</hi> is largely diſcourſt by the Obſervator beyond any force of reaſon which the Animadverſor hath uſed to enforce the contrary. His Majeſtie acknowledged much of this to the <hi>Scotts,</hi> whoſe preparations were in all reſpects like ours, and which his Majeſtie found to be <hi>Non tam contra quam praeter authoritatem Regis.</hi> after he had preſt the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſors arguments as warmely, as now he doth againſt other of his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, though yet ſuffering under the great calamitie of his Royall diſpleaſure. But to ſay little of that which is ſo notorious to us all of this Kingdome; Let us looke over to <hi>France,</hi> and there we may ſee thoſe who were as much Proteſtants as we, that levied armes againſt their Kings commands, accompanied with his preſence, and yet our King never thought them the worſe Chriſtians or Subjects for that, and therefore made himſelfe a partizan with them in their very cauſe; ſo clearely was the piety and lawfulneſſe of ſuch an act at that time reconciled to his Majeſties conſcience and underſtanding. All which the Animadverſor muſt needs confeſſe, unleſſe he will owne the preſent Declarations of the <hi>Rochelers,</hi> who with execrations of us ſay (upon the event of their warre) that the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham's</hi> deſigne was to deſtroy and eate them up; and that they had preſerved their liberties and Religion from any adulterate mixture of Popery, had they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeene him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But according to the Animadverſor, It is impoſſible a King ſhould ruine his Kingdome, becauſe he ſhall alwayes have the Major part with him.</hi> But moderne miſeries ſhew us the contrary, witneſſe the neare depopulated Principalities of <hi>Germany.</hi> But to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Argument with like reaſon, I ſay, that after a King ſhall have deſtroyed the Minor part of his Kingdome with his Major, why may he not then, by ſome differences in the Major part, be a cauſe even to bring that to deſtruction too? But without ſuppoſing ſuch a Fate, why may he not, <hi>Nero</hi>-like, for pleaſure ſake, deſire that all the heads of the Major part ſtood but upon one necke, that ſo he might chop them off at a blow? Seing then ſuch a King may ruine his Kingdom, (by lamentable diſtreſſes &amp; depopulations) and if a Parliament hath the power to hinder it, it doth that which it is bound to doe, and which is neither againſt the perſon, or genuine authoritie of the King unleſſe we can apprehend a Kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie without a Kingdome (which is the object it extends to and acts in, and which we have proved he may deſtroy) and with out which the Animadverſor muſt needs reduce ſuch a King to a barer Title, than he ſaid our Parliament would reduce our King to.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
